Register of the I. Babel' letters
Hoover Institution Archives
I. Babel' letters
1925-1939
2006C32
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Letters to family members relating to Russian literature and personal affairs. Includes typed transcripts. Photocopy.
Babel', I. (Isaak), 1894-1941.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Isaak Babel', Russian/Soviet writer, was born in 1894, in Odessa. In 1915 he moved to Petrograd, where he met Maksim Gorky, who became his friend and mentor. He published Babel's two short stories in the Letopis' magazine. Gorky advised the aspiring writer to gain more life experience. According to one of Babel's stories, Doroga (The Road), he served on the Romanian front until early December 1917. He resurfaced in Petrograd in March 1918 as a reporter for Gorky's newspaper, Novaya zhizn (New Life). During the Russian Civil War, Babel' worked for the publishing house of the Odessa Gubkom (regional CPSU Committee), in the food procurement unit in the Narkompros (People's Commissariat of Education), and in a typographic printing office.
After the end of the Civil War, Babel' worked as a reporter for Zaria Vostoka (The Dawn of the Orient).
Babel' married Yevgenia Gronfein on August 9, 1919, in Odessa.
In 1920, Babel' was assigned to the First Cavalry Army and witnessed a military campaign in the Polish-Soviet War of 1920. He documented the horrors of that in the Konarmeiskiy Dnevnik, 1920 God (1920 Diary), which he later used to write Konarmiya (Red Cavalry), a collection of short stories.
In 1924, his mother and sister with her family immigrated to Belgium; in 1925 his wife immigrated to Paris. Babel' visited them several times during his trips to France; in 1929, his daughter Natalie was born. Babel' wrote letters to his family from 1925 through 1939, when he was arrested and put in prison.
Babel' was arrested in May 1939; his writings were confiscated and disappeared. He was tortured during interrogations. In January 1940 he was executed, and his name disappeared from literary life: it was removed from literary dictionaries and encyclopedias and taken off school and university syllabi. He was rehabilitated in 1954.
Scope and Content of Collection
Letters relating to Russian literature and personal affairs from Babel' to his family members: mother, Fania Babel'; sister, Mera Chapochnikoff, and her husband Grigorii; and Babel's wife and daughter. Includes typed transcripts. Photocopy.
It should be noted that some original letters do not have corresponding transcripts, while some transcripts were made from letters unavailable in this collection.
Russian literature.
- Correspondence, 1925-1939
  - 1925 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Two loose pages, undated
    - February 23
    - May 12
    - June 5
    - July 15
    - August 21
    - November 5, 16, 20
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes two letters of November 5, 1925.
  - 1926 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Undated
      Three letters to Babel's mother and one letter to his sister; one letter without beginning; and one letter from Babel's mother.
    - January 1, 6, 26
      Unfinished letter.
    - February 8
      Page 2 only.
    - March 22, 29, 31
    - April 5, 16
      Includes a letter to sister of April 5, 1926 (two copies), and a letter to mother of April 16, 1926, containing an undated letter from Babel's mother (two copies).
    - May 2
    - July 16, 30
    - August 4, 14
    - September 7, 10, 16, 17, 23, 29
      Includes two letters of September 17, 1926.
    - October 3, 13, 23, 27
    - November 2, 5, 10, 15, 29
      Includes two letters of November 2, 1926 (to mother and sister), and a letter of November 10, 1926, and one loose page (beginning is missing).
    - December 8, 9, 17
  - 1927 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Undated
      Letter from Fania Aronovna (Babel's mother) to Mera (Babel's sister).
    - January 3, 11, 22, 28
    - February 8, 11
    - March 1, 5, 7, 11, 18, 26, 30
    - April 6, 17, 23, 30
    - May 8, 28
    - June 12, 16, 24
  - 1928 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - April 2, 28
    - May 10, 21
    - June 3, 29
    - September 30
    - October 1, 3, 17, 20, 22, 26, 28, 29, 30
    - November 5, 6, 11, 13, 16, 19, 23, 25
    - December 1, 4, 6, 9, 13, 15, 20, 23, 25
  - 1929 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - January 1, 2, 7, 10, 14, 17, 19, 22, 29
    - February 6, 9, 13, 20, 23, 28
      The postcard of February 23, 1929, was copied next to the postcard of July 20, 1929. See Box 1, Folder 6.
    - March 4, 14, 16, 19, 29, 30
    - April 2, 4, 8, 10, 12, 15, 17, 19, 21, 24, 27
    - May 1, 5, 7, 9, 11, 15, 17, 21, 24, 27, 30
    - June 1, 3, 5, 13, 14, 19, 25, 28, 29
  - 1929 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - July 4, 6, 9, 11, 15, 20, 26, 28
    - August 1, 7, 8, 10, 11, 14, 17, 20, 27, 31
    - September 2, 4, 6, 12, 14, 19, 25, 26
    - October 2, 4, 7, 10, 17, 26, 29
    - November 2, 5, 7, 11, 15, 18
    - December 2, 6, 14, 21, 24, 27, 30
  - 1930 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - January 10, 16, 21, 30
    - February 4, 5, 9, 16, 17, 20, 24
    - March 6, 10, 28
    - April 1, 16, 21, 27
    - May 10, 13, 18, 20, 25, 26, 31
    - June 7, 14, 19, 20, 23, 25, 30
    - July 1, 6, 16, 22, 28, 31
    - August 3, 6, 12, 17, 19, 24, 29
    - September 2, 15, 21, 24, 25, 29
      The postcard of September 25, 1930, was copied next to the postcard of December 15, 1930.
    - October 6, 8, 13, 18, 21, 25
    - November 4, 5, 7, 8, 9, 12, 17, 23, 27
    - December 10, 14, 15, 20, 25, 28, 31
  - 1931 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - January 2, 14, 21, 27
      Additional copy of the January 2 postcard can be found next to the postcard of February 25, 1931. The postcard of January 27, 1931, was copied next to the postcard of April 19, 1931.
    - February 4, 8, 11, 19, 25, 27
    - March 2, 5, 11, 15, 17, 18, 24, 28
    - April 5, 11, 12, 16, 19, 24, 25
      The postcard of April 24, 1931, was copied next to the postcard of July 15, 1931. See Box 1, Folder 9.
    - May 3, 5, 7, 12, 14, 15, 21, 24
    - June 1, 5, 11, 17, 20, 26, 29
      Includes two postcards of June 20, 1931, and a letter and a postcard of June 26, 1931. The postcard of June 29, 1931, was copied next to the postcard of July 9, 1931. See Box 1, Folder 9.
  - 1931 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - July 2, 7, 9, 12, 15, 17, 18, 20, 22, 26, 30, 31
      The postcard of July 2, 1931, was copied next to the postcard of October 21, 1931; the postcard of July 22, 1931, was copied next to the postcard of October 6, 1931. Includes two postcards of July 31, 1931.
    - August 3, 4, 11, 13, 30
    - September 1, 6, 7, 15, 18, 25, 26, 28, 30
    - October 1, 4, 6, 11, 14, 16, 20, 21, 22, 31
    - November 8, 14, 18, 19, 27, 30
    - December 4, 7, 12, 16, 17, 21, 25
  - 1932 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Undated
    - January 2, 7, 12, 25
    - February 4
    - March 3, 16
    - April 5, 9, 11, 12, 17, 23, 29
      The postcard of April 29, 1932, was copied next to the postcard of May 27, 1932.
    - May 6, 11, 19, 27
    - August 5, 17
    - September 4, 19, 22, 25
    - October 2, 4, 6, 12, 17, 20, 22, 27, 28, 29, 30
    - November 2,4, 6, 8, 15, 16, 24
    - December 11, 15
  - 1933 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - January 1
      The postcard was copied next to the postcard of April 24, 1933.
    - February 4, 22
    - March 4
    - April 5, 15, 18, 24, 25
    - May 2, 5, 11, 18, 20, 24, 28
      The postcard of May 2, 1933, was copied next to the postcard of December 9, 1933.
    - June 18, 26
    - July 2, 6, 10, 13, 19
    - September 1, 3, 21
    - October 7, 18, 29
    - November 8, 12, 16, 26
    - December 4, 9, 12, 13, 19, 21, 23, 29
  - 1934 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - January 8, 15
    - February 4, 13, 18, 25
    - March 2, 3, 7, 15, 26
    - April 2, 5, 14, 23, 29
    - May 13, 26
    - June 8, 18, 20, 23
    - July 10
    - October 16
    - November 14, 26
    - December 13, 23
  - 1935 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - January 7, 14
    - February 3, 18, 24
    - March 14, 23, 24, 31
    - April 17
    - June 13, 15, 27, 28
    - July 1, 4, 11, 20
    - August 5, 8, 21
    - September 4, 11, 12, 19, 21, 23, 30
    - October 3, 9, 13, 19, 23
    - November 13, 21
    - December 13, 15
  - 1936 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - January 7, 28
    - February 2, 15, 26
    - March, 1, 5, 18
    - April 15, 20, 21, 22, 26
      The postcard of April 2, 1936, was copied next to the postcard of November 21, 1936; the postcard of April 15, 1936, was copied next to the postcard of June 7, 1936.
    - May 27
    - June 2, 7, 12, 15, 17, 19, 24, 28
      The postcard of June 2, 1936, was copied next to the postcard of August 28, 1936.
    - July 12, 22, 30
    - August 8, 10, 13, 20, 28, 30
    - September 1, 4, 5, 10, 17, 22, 24
      The postcard of September 5, 1936, was copied next to the postcard of October 23, 1936.
    - October 4, 14, 19, 23, 25, 29, 30
    - November 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 30
    - December 22
  - 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Undated
    - January 2, 6, 8, 11, 27
      The postcard of January 2, 1937, was copied next to the postcard of December 1, 1937; the postcard of January 11, 1937, was copied next to the postcard of December 27, 1937.
    - February 1, 19
    - March 5, 11, 13, 18, 28
    - April 13, 20, 26
    - May 1, 7, 10, 17
      The postcard of May 1, 1937, was copied next to the postcard of December 12, 1937.
    - July 10, 13, 19, 30
    - August 2, 26
    - September 6, 16, 19
      The postcard of September 6, 1937, was copied next to the postcard of October 11, 1937.
    - October 4, 6, 11, 14, 20
      The postcard of October 14, 1937, was copied next to the postcard of November 7, 1937.
    - November 3, 5, 7, 12, 16, 20, 26, 27
    - December 1, 7, 10, 14, 19, 22, 24, 27
  - 1938 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Undated
    - January 5, 9, 11, 14, 31
    - February 4, 9, 11, 15, 18, 19, 20, 27
    - March 7, 12, 20, 24, 25
    - April 4, 6, 16, 20, 29
    - May 10, 13, 15, 24
      The postcard of May 13, 1938, was copied next to the postcard of June 21, 1938.
    - June 1, 7, 12, 17, 21, 24
    - July 10, 20, 24, 26, 30, 31
    - August 3, 4, 12, 16, 18, 19, 22, 25
    - September 11, 20, 24, 26
      Includes two postcards of September 11, 1938.
    - October 3, 9, 19, 25, 30
      Includes two postcards of October 9, 1938.
    - November 2, 9, 15, 30
    - December 2, 25
- Transcripts of Correspondence, 1926-1939
  - 1926 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Undated
      Two undated letters from Babel's mother and one undated letter from Babel'.
    - January 26
    - February
    - April 6, 16
    - May 2
    - July 16
    - August 14, 30
    - September 17, 23
    - October 13, 23
    - November 2, 10, 15, 29
      Includes two letters of November 2.
    - December 8, 9
  - 1927 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - January 3, 11
    - February 2
    - March 5, 7, 18, 26
    - April 12
    - May 8
    - June 12
    - From mother, December 31
  - 1928 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - April 2, 28
    - May 21
    - June 3
    - October 1, 3, 9, 20, 22, 26, 28, 29, 30
    - November 6, 11, 13, 25, 29
    - December 1, 4, 6, 13, 15, 25
  - 1929 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - January 7, 10, 14, 17, 19
    - February 9, 13
    - March 4, 14, 16, 19, 29, 30
    - April 2, 4, 7, 8, 10, 12, 17, 19, 21, 24
    - May 1, 9, 11, 15, 17, 21, 24, 27, 30
    - June 2, 5, 13, 14, 19, 25, 28, 29
    - July 4, 6, 9, 11, 26, 28
    - August 7, 8, 10, 11, 14, 17, 20, 27, 31
    - September 2, 6, 14, 19, 25, 26
    - October 4, 7, 10, 17, 26, 29
    - November 5, 7, 11, 15, 18, 23
    - December 2, 6, 14, 21, 24, 27, 29
  - 1930 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - January 8, 10, 31, 30
    - February 5, 9, 16, 17, 20, 24
      Includes two letters of February 9, 1930.
    - March 6, 10, 28
    - April 1, 16, 21, 27
    - May 10, 13, 18, 20, 25, 31
    - June 7, 10, 14, 23, 25, 30
    - July 16, 19, 28, 31
    - August 3, 6, 17, 24, 29
    - September 2, 8, 13, 28, 21, 24, 25
    - October 6, 8, 13, 18, 21, 25
    - November 4, 5, 7, 8, 9, 12, 17, 23, 27
    - December 10, 14, 15, 20, 25, 28
  - 1931 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - January 4, 8, 21
    - February 8
    - March 5, 6, 11, 17, 18
    - May 3, 5, 7, 12, 15, 19, 24, 28
    - June 1, 5, 11, 17, 20, 26
      Includes two letters of June 1, 1931, and of June 17, 1931.
    - July 3, 7, 12, 17, 20, 26, 30, 31
    - August 3, 4, 11, 13, 17, 30
    - September 1, 7, 15, 18, 22, 25, 26, 28, 30
    - November 18, 19
    - December 4, 25
  - 1932 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - January 2, 7, 15
    - March 16
    - April 9, 17
    - August 17
    - September 19, 25
    - October 17, 20, 27, 28
    - November 6, 8, 15, 24
      Includes two letters of November 15, 1932.
    - December 15
  - 1933 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - February 4, 22, 26
    - March 4
    - May 29
    - July 6, 13, 19
    - September 29
    - October 7, 18
    - November 16, 26
  - 1934 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - January 15
    - February 4, 18
    - March 26
    - April 2, 23
    - June 23
    - October 16
  - 1935 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - January 7, 14
    - February 3, 17, 18
    - March 23, 27, 31
    - April 17
    - June 13, 15, 27
    - July 4, 15, 20
    - August 5, 8, 9, 21
    - September 12, 19, 21, 23, 30
    - October 3, 9, 19, 30
    - November 23
    - December 5, 9, 15, 27
  - 1936 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - February 26
    - April 21, 22
    - June 2, 12, 19, 28
    - August 20
    - September 1, 4, 24
    - October 7, 10, 14
    - November 2, 3, 5, 7, 12, 20, 24, 30
    - December 7, 24
  - 1937 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - January 6, 8
    - February 1, 19
    - March 5, 13, 18
    - April 20
    - May 7, 10, 17
    - July 10, 13, 19
    - August 2, 4, 16
    - September 16, 19
    - October 6, 20
    - November 3, 5, 16, 27
    - December 1, 19, 22, 24
  - 1938 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - January 3, 5, 11, 14, 26, 31
    - February 4, 11, 18
    - March 7, 12
    - April 6, 16, 30, 29
    - May 4, 10, 13, 15, 24
      Includes two letters of May 24, 1938.
    - June 1, 8, 12, 17, 24
    - July 10, 20, 24, 25, 26, 30
      Includes two letters of July 26, 1938.
    - August 3, 4, 12, 16, 18, 19, 22
    - September 11, 20, 24
    - November 2, 9, 15, 30
    - December 2, 25
  - 1939 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - January 2
    - March 31
    - May 10